We are in Calabria,
in the extreme south of Italy.
Welcome to San Lucas, 4,000 inhabitants,
a seemingly very poor village.
And yet, it is the high place
of the Ndrangheta, the most powerful,
and the richest mafia in the world.
These little cobbled streets have seen
birth of the Calabrian octopus,
almost 200 years ago.
She never left.
However, curiously, in
the village, the old inhabitants,
have never heard of the Ndrangheta.
- This village is famous
for the Ndrangheta, right?
- What is that ? It doesn't exist
no, we are good people.
- You agree ?
- Yes, yes, I agree with him.
We can't steal anything since
that there is no money.
There is no work here,
there is nothing at all.
The Calabrian Ndrangheta brews
yet 53 billion euros per year.
But she remains very discreet.
Here, the law of silence reigns.
Every Sunday morning, men
discuss on the town hall square,
and in this very pious region,
women are responsible for assisting
at high mass, dressed in black.
- The body, the blood of
Jesus Christ, our Lord.
In this small village, most of the
residents have a relative in the mafia.
This is even the case of the priest, Pino Strangio.
He's the only person to have
agreed to tell us about the Ndrangheta.
If he chose the priesthood, 3 of
his first cousins ​​are in prison.
- They chose their path.
These are people who are in their thirties and one
of them has been in prison for more than 10 years.
For a drug case.
Calabrians are rare
who, like Pino Strangio,
dare to confess to their family's crimes.
However, these are not the stories
lacking. Here, the Ndrangheta is everywhere.
Calabria is the tip of Italy,
just opposite Sicily.
It is also the cradle of the Ndrangheta.
Nearly 200 clans share
the territory and its annual loot,
is 53 billion euros. As much
of money than McDonald's and Ikea combined.
The Ndrangheta is powerful and
present in the 4 corners of the world.
Its first source of
income is drugs.
She is number one on
the global c**** market.
- This is where
drugs enter Europe.
Because the port is
controlled by the Ndrangheta.
The Guardia di Finanza does
regularly spectacular seizures.
- Just with that, we buy ourselves
a small apartment in Paris.
Each family of the Ndrangheta
also gets rich by taking the pizzo,
mafia tax. A man filmed
the extortions of which he was the victim.
- There, I put a wad of
10 million lire on the table.
And those who refuse
to pay, are executed.
- I will fight until I die
hoping it's natural.
And those who denounce
lead a life on borrowed time.
- It's a weapon-proof window.
There I can drink my
coffee quietly.
But most of
victims of the Ndrangheta,
come from its own ranks.
The Calabrian mafia is over-armed and
don't hesitate to let the powder speak
to settle accounts.
The worst enemy of the Ndrangheta,
it's the anti-prosecutor
mafia Nicolas Gratery.
It is protected 24 hours a day.
He leads long investigations and
brings down godfathers by the dozens.
He also deciphered the codes
secrets of the Ndrangheta.
- If it is necessary, you will have to
kill your father, your mother, your brother,
your sister and your whole family.
But he has difficulty finding witnesses.
This mafia which has no supreme leader,
is an association of families.
There is no repentance. These new
members swear never to betray.
The Italian police succeeded
to film an induction.
Very rare images.
- Either you follow the rules or
you keep a bullet in your magazine.
This one is for you.
Investigation into this mysterious mafia
ultra-Catholic campaigns,
who hides his fortune and
rules part of the world.
5 a.m.
In this port in southern Italy,
the police are deployed.
We are in Gioia Tauro,
50 kilometers from Reggio,
west of Calabria.
Impeccable uniform,
tie knot tightly.
Alessandro Barbera, Colonel
of the Guardia di Finanza,
leads an anti-operation
large-scale drug.
He has information: One of
ships arriving this morning,
contains a lot of cocaine.
- It is the ship which
transports containers,
from South America.
It is this ship that is being targeted.
The Ndrangheta installed members
mafia families in Colombia,
in Ecuador or Mexico to buy
drugs produced on site,
and ship it. UNITED STATES,
Europe, Australia,
narcotics are sent
in the 4 corners of the world,
wherever the Ndrangheta is present.
Half the drugs that the mafia,
distributed in Europe transits through
the port of Gioia Tauro, in Calabria.
At each operation
of fist, Colonel Barbera,
has around thirty men
to monitor unloading.
He and his men watch
up close to the dockers.
Many of them do
part of the Ndrangheta.
According to a recent official anti-mafia report.
- This is where the
drugs enter Europe.
Because this port is
controlled by the Ndrangheta.
Between the colonel and the Ndrangheta,
it is a war of attrition that is being played out.
For years now, every
suspect boat is escorted by customs,
to prevent the drug
not be thrown overboard,
and recovered by stars
quickly before arriving at the port.
- It's a daily battle
between the Ndrangheta and us,
they try everything to escape us and us,
we are doing everything we can to stop them.
From the moment we reinforce
a particular type of control,
this criminal organization
immediately finds,
a new means of concealment.
And indeed, in this game
cat and mouse,
the Calabrian mafia has
always one step ahead.
- How many containers did you take down?
- Since the operation
started around 7 a.m. this morning,
we have already lowered 142 containers.
More than 1000 containers to control,
a colossal job.
But the information received by
the colonel are very precise.
54 of them were quickly isolated.
They contain bananas.
Hundreds of boxes are
taken out of each container.
And inspect.
- What is this dog looking for?
- An odor that is associated
to a game for him.
Here, we usually find some s***.
Finally, a container holds
the attention of La Guardia's men.
The colonel does not wish to reveal
the detail he put on this track,
while the investigation is ongoing.
But he is certain,
this container hides a double bottom.
He has him boned.
Police officers film the scene.
In a few minutes,
the container is ripped open.
In the ground, leaves
lead are hiding something.
This metal makes it possible to lure
customs scanners.
- What is this ?
- It's a c**** loaf.
The double bottom is full of drugs.
- So, how many are there?
Did you count them?
- I'm not finished yet,
but I would say around 50 kilos.
Already 50 kilos of drugs,
an exceptional seizure.
But the double bottom of the container
contains much more.
The catch is in fact historic.
- As you can see.
This container was specifically created,
to accommodate a double bottom.
This double bottom was made to measure,
to hide the cocaine.
For the colonel, this is something new.
The cocaine business is
so profitable for the Ndrangheta,
that the mafia spends a fortune
to corrupt many people,
in the transport chain
to the container manufacturer.
The loaves are now counted
by dozens, so many,
that several people are needed
to transport them.
- Everything fits in one car?
- No, we put some in another car.
The drugs are transported
at the Guardia di Finanza barracks,
on the port of Gioia Tauro.
The pines are numbered then weighed
one after the other.
- 1,185 kilos.
In total, 101 loaves of c****.
- On average for retail consumption,
each kilo of c**** is cut 4 times.
One kilo roughly becomes 4 kilos.
On average, one gram of c****
is sold for €60 on the market.
So if you count quickly,
each one kilo package,
brings into the coffers of organizations
criminal charges approximately €250,000.
With a kilo like that, we could
buy a small apartment in Paris.
- It is the last.
- Then show me the total.
- 118,570 kilos.
118 kilos of cocaine purchased from producers,
according to United Nations experts.
€236,000 for a resale price
of more than 28 million euros.
This is one of the largest seizures of
the year for the Italian authorities.
And a colossal loss for the Ndrangheta.
It is now necessary to verify that it is
lots of c**** thanks to a chemical test.
The liquid turns dark blue,
sign of a very pure c****.
A new investigation begins to identify
the cartel that ships the c****.
The starting point, this logo.
- Look, there is this symbol
with 2 letters "T.E".
The investigations into the Ndrangheta are
led by an anti-mafia prosecutor.
He's one of the men
the most endangered in Italy.
Armored car, armed escort.=,
his 3 bodyguards
don't let go of him for a single moment,
and this for 26 years.
Nicolas Gratery put in
prison more than 1,000 mafiosi.
His vocation was born here, in this
college of the Calabrian countryside,
where the children of N'dranghetta
made the law.
- That was my class on the first floor.
From there, I felt, I breathed their
violence that started on the sidewalk,
and that I found in class.
This was opposed to the education that
I had received in my family.
Nicolas Gratery will devote his life
in the fight against the 'Ndrangheta.
Far from the path taken
by his class neighbors.
- Some chose
classic professions,
many more were killed
and many others are in prison.
- How much ?
- At least ten are
detained and 6 or 7 died.
If Nicolas Gratery is threatened with death,
is that he is not satisfied
to put criminals in prison.
He also managed to dissect
the functioning of the Ndrangheta,
and updated the rites which govern
entry into this secret society.
- There is an initiation which lasts 1 to 2 years,
during this, the person
must perform acts of courage,
to show what she
is capable, he's tough.
How do you enter the Ndrangheta?
Word of Greek origin which
means courage, ardor.
Recently, thanks to cameras
hidden, the men of Nicolas Gratery,
managed to film an induction.
- Repeat after me: I swear to deny,
everything up to the 7th generation,
the entire criminal society
recognized by me so far...
To preserve the honor of
my brothers full of wisdom.
The new member integrates
a family for life.
In case of betrayal, he only has 2
solutions to be judged by one's peers,
or kill oneself.
- The Oath of Poison! Pellet
of cyanide, to poison you.
Or you take a weapon,
bullets in the magazine,
you should always keep some
a. This one is for you.
- From that moment on, there was no
has more than the Ndrangheta that exists,
and if necessary, you will have to kill your father,
your mother, your brother, your sister, your family,
in order to preserve the very existence
of the Ndrangheta, it is fundamental.
In exchange for its services, the Ndrangheta
offers new members,
protection of the clan
and comfortable income,
provided that this one
This respects the rules.
Nicolas Gratery knows the
punishments inflicted on those who sin,
and there are all kinds of examples.
- Depending on the fault we commit.
The sanction may be to be suspended
meeting for 3 or 4 months.
We can get our heads
in the toilet or in the coal.
Having to wear an animal head,
pee on your leg.
These are acts of humiliation which
can sometimes lead to death.
The magistrate even deciphered the codes
secrets that some clans use
to communicate discreetly.
- This is one of the 30 codes known so far.
Information accumulated over the long term
of 30 years of investigations and searches.
Here is the last entry
from a few months ago.
These symbols represent the structure
hierarchy of a clan of San Luca,
the stronghold of the Calabrian mafia.
It took years of work for the prosecutor
Gratery to know everything about the mafia.
These investigations can last several years,
these net shots are
often spectacular.
2 a.m. Criminal Squad
from Reggio di Calabria.
200 police officers were mobilized by the
magistrate for an anti-mafia operation
very large in scale.
Last night, 29 people suspected
to be bigwigs of the mafia,
must be questioned for
rigging of public markets,
and widespread extortion.
A few minutes before departure, envelopes,
containing all the information on the
Targets are distributed to each team.
So far, only a handful of
police knew the objectives.
The prosecutor wanted to avoid leaks
by possible corrupt officials.
- For the team that will challenge him,
the objective is kept secret.
Until the last moment.
Inspector d'Agostino is in charge
to arrest a godfather.
The main target of the operation,
Salvatore Aquino.
Aquino is not just anyone
within the Ndrangheta.
At 70, he is the head of a powerful
clan that rules Gioiosa Ionica,
neighboring town of Salerno.
He has already been sentenced to
15 years in prison in 1999,
for international sex trafficking.
He is now on supervised release.
He runs his business as a family.
His nephews are currently incarcerated.
They were arrested 3 years ago
years while they were on the run.
Here they are on the day of their arrest,
filmed by the carabinieri.
They were found in 2
perfectly concealed hiding places,
in the basement of a house,
under a removable staircase.
And in this false ceiling.
To escape the police, the mafiosi
often resort to these bunkers.
They can spend several
months, even years.
On the other side of the parking lot, Matteo
and his men in turn discover,
the identity of the mafioso they are going to arrest.
Leonardo Capo Greco.
At 38, he belongs to a family
of Cidernos, the Commissos.
He is wanted for corruption
and extortion.
He would be his clan's accountant.
- These are figures
important parts of the Ndrangheta.
The police will intervene simultaneously,
to prevent information from circulating,
and that certain suspects
escape the dragnet.
At the time of departure,
It’s time for final instructions.
- You will stay with him from
moment when we enter, when he goes to pee,
when he goes to change,
when he packs his bag.
- We are going to an area of ​​Calabria
where this clan we're going to hit
already has a past, a history.
Its members were involved
in many surveys.
The police do not wear vests
bulletproof or heavy weapons.
The mafiosi put up no resistance.
They leave it to their armies of lawyers
care to get them out of prison gently.
Around sixty police cars
leave the parking lot in column.
200 men from the criminal brigade
rush across Calabria.
1 hour later, the vehicles disperse,
to reach the 3 targeted cities.
Leonardo Capo Greco
lives in this large villa.
The police may be discreet,
the neighbors' dog notices their presence.
They must quickly
enter the garden.
You have to climb the gate.
This police officer is responsible for monitoring
the back of the house.
In front of the house, 3 men
are on the front line.
A fourth remains behind.
He watches for any movement at the windows.
- We are the police.
- That's what I see.
- We need to do a search.
- You are welcome.
- You're alone at home ?
- Yes.
Despite this nocturnal irruption,
Leonardo Capo Greco appears serene.
In the house everything seems calm,
but the police remain vigilant.
- Do you have weapons at home?
- No. I have a gun permit,
but there is none here.
Investigators search the house.
If this man works
officially in the construction industry,
he is suspected of laundering
part of the Ndrangheta fortune.
He probably doesn't hide any money at home.
The investigators are rather at
search for accounting documents,
which would prove money laundering.
We found elements
who can serve us,
but generally, for all good
check, we need more time.
So at the office,
we can calmly watch everything
equipment that we take with us.
Capo Greco is taken towards
The police headquarters.
At the same time, 5 kilometers away,
the men of the criminal brigade,
take stock with police officers
uniform who have just scouted the scene.
They will question the one who is designated
as the godfather of the Salvatore Aquino clan.
- Are there surveillance cameras?
- There are lights everywhere.
There are big white spotlights.
They light up the entrance to the building.
Direction the Godfather's residence.
On the spot, surprise.
The mafioso who would be sitting on
tens of millions of euros,
acquired illegally,
does not own a palace.
He preferred to build
a building to accommodate his entire family.
He is content with a modest apartment
on the third floor in the area.
Mafia bosses are discreet,
but only on the front.
- Search.
- Do you have a warrant?
- Yes, you can get dressed.
The man we arrest looks like
to a quiet grandfather,
far from the image of the mafioso in a suit
striped, a cigar in his mouth.
At home, no weapons, no bodyguards.
For 2 hours, the police
go get documents,
proving that they are rigging public markets.
- We'll take you to the office.
Direction the anti-mafia service.
It's 7 a.m.
Return to Reggio di Calabria.
The 29 arrested were
taken back to police headquarters,
before which they gathered
families and friends of the suspects.
They are going to be imprisoned.
But before that, justice makes them
parade in front of the cameras.
In order of importance.
A staging which is also
a communication operation,
intended for all
Calabrian society.
Salvatore Aquino, the alleged godfather, is the
1ᵉʳ to be exhibited in front of the Italian media.
Leonardo Capo Greco is going out,
him, in fourth position.
They are all accused
aggravated extortion,
and rigging of public markets,
but above all of mafia association.
A crime that only exists in Italy.
This allows a person to be convicted
as soon as a link is established between it,
and a criminal organization.
Punishment then incurred: 15 years in prison.
Prosecutor Gratery invited
around thirty journalists,
for a press conference.
Here it doesn't happen
just like in France.
Full details of the operation
of the night will be reviewed.
The identities of those arrested,
the reason for their indictment,
will be delivered to journalists.
The moment is historic for the prosecutor.
- It's a great day for
the prosecution and the police.
The members of the Ndrangheta,
arrested last night,
are great figures
Calabrian octopus.
Every mass arrest
offers the prosecutor a platform,
to address public opinion.
Faced with the most powerful mafia in the world,
Nicolas Gratery wants to get the message across,
that the Italian State is present in Calabria.
- If we do these press conferences,
it's to tell people,
that they can trust
in us, that the State exists,
that they should go to the police,
the Guardia di Finanza and the carabinieri,
to denounce the mafiosi.
Around twenty people arrested
that night and still in prison.
On the other hand, Salvatore Aquino, the boss
presumed, was released 1 month later.
As usual, his lawyers found
the flaw, the good procedural flaw.
50 kilometers from Reggio, in the city
from Palmi, a man saw a lump in his stomach.
We will meet him
in this strange building.
38 surveillance cameras,
barbed wire on the surrounding walls,
and elite armed police officers in the courtyard.
We are at Gaetano Saffioti,
his house became his prison.
Gaetano has a wife and a child.
We will not film them.
He doesn't want to put them in danger
because there is a price on his head.
- Coffee, you take it
still at home?
- Yes.
- Never at the bar?
- I can't go to the bar anymore.
My situation is a bit complicated.
Many bars don't accept you because
they fear there will be an attack.
And then we put the other customers in
embarrassment, we should clear the bar
and that's a bit complicated.
Gaetano runs a business
who makes concrete.
He is threatened with death by the Ndrangheta.
He's what the mobsters call
an infamous one for having broken the omerta,
the law of silence.
To survive, he had to transform
his bunker dwelling.
- That's armored glass
bulletproof weapons.
It allows me to enjoy my coffee
without being in danger.
- You mean risk-free?
- Without the risk of an attack occurring.
- Since when,
do you live behind this glass?
- It's been 12 years, 9 months
and 23 days today.
But it's been 12 years, 9 months and 23
days that I feel like a free man.
It may seem paradoxical,
but before, it was hell.
The authorities suggested other
parades to thwart all types of attacks.
- On this side which gives
directly on the road.
We had to raise the wall.
And we reinforced it with a wall
made of iron to protect us from bullets,
which would be taken from the street.
At the top we had to cover
with a kind of roof,
to prevent someone from throwing a bomb.
It all started in the early 2000s.
It has been 20 years since Gaetano
pay the pizzo, the mafia tax.
- He used to come, he used to sit here,
he called: “Prepare the money.”
You had to prepare the money.
- And you had to pay in cash?
- In cash, of course, it does not
should not leave any traces.
He sat down in one of his chairs,
I had already prepared the money.
I took it and gave it.
It's 2001.
The Ndrangheta has already
extorted 2 million euros,
at many times,
Gaetano tried not to pay,
but the mafia families,
systematically punished,
his attempts at rebellion.
- This is one of the trucks that was
burned. That's when I was being deceitful.
I wasn't paying.
And they responded with retaliation.
He set fire to trucks,
to excavators.
In all, there are around thirty
construction vehicles that were destroyed.
One of his employees had to
even set fire to his machine,
while a big arm of the mafia
pointed a gun at his head.
The more time passed, the more
the amounts requested increased.
Exasperated, Gaetano alone finally decides to react.
- That's a camera
monitoring inserted into the wall,
and which I used to record
all appointments,
that I was obliged to have
with the men of the Ndrangheta.
For months he recorded
extortion scenes.
In addition to paying the pizzo to
the Palmi family where he works,
he must also pay back money
to the clan of Rosarno and Gioia Tauro,
who had control over neighboring towns,
that he crossed to deliver
materials to its customers.
This is the particularity of the Ndrangheta,
unlike other mafias,
where there is a leader,
for the entire organization,
in Calabria, the region is divided
in more than 160 territories,
with a leader per sector. There is
a tax per territory crossed.
Gaetano was thus extorted by 3 clans.
- 3 times for the same work
to 3 different clans.
That's how it works. It is
as if you were going to a foreign country,
where we pay customs correctly
because we cross it.
Gaetano thus accumulates several
recording hours,
dozens of examples of his hell
every day, at any time of the day.
- I open the drawer, I take a wad
of 10 million lire at the time.
And I put it on the table
even showing it on camera.
10 million lire, or more than €7,000.
To be sure to convince justice,
Gaetano puts a battle plan in place.
He takes all the risks.
Here he intentionally shows the camera,
that he is holding a wad of notes
in the hand, proof of extortion.
But one day, a mafioso realizes
that something has changed in his office.
- He realizes that there is a
surveillance camera and he says to me:
“That’s your problem, what do I think?
have to do with a surveillance camera?"
The man warns Gaetano.
He leaves it there, because he is convinced
that he is afraid, that he will do nothing,
that omerta, like
always, will impose itself on him.
Except that Gaetano decides
to break the law of silence.
He delivers his recordings to justice.
48 members of 3 families are arrested
and sentenced to up to 16 years in prison.
The police will also seize for 50
million euros worth of real estate.
This dragnet marks the beginning of
pressure for him to retract.
And death threats against him.
- “Very soon you will receive in the body
45 fragments of p**** bullet.
That way you won't get bored
from Palmi, but from the earth."
- Is this a clear threat?
- A clear threat, a bullet
pistol for each person arrested.
The Ndrangheta, established everywhere, is
pressure on its customers and suppliers.
Gaetano's company loses
90% of its turnover.
- Just after the denunciations,
it was the apocalypse.
Everyone has disappeared, the workers,
banks, suppliers,
the customers, the desert.
Gaetano has become what we
calls Calabria an infamous person.
And yet, 13 years
later he feels free.
- That's my life, she
is reduced to around twenty steps.
This is the distance from my house
and my office after having had my coffee,
This is the only journey I take,
from one building to another.
It is the life of the one who
chose to live legally.
It's the price to pay, but
I'm happy to pay it.
Thanks to all these protections,
Gaetano continues to live,
but he is locked up at home.
This is an isolated case in Calabria,
because there, those who defy the mafia,
pay for it with their lives.
Just in Siderno,
32 recent assassinations,
are still not elucidated.
The Ndrangheta is suspected every time
times, but no one testifies.
Mario goes to this cemetery 4
times a week for 10 years now.
He can't mourn
his son shot in the head.
- The marble is missing,
I didn't want to wear it.
It's like it's all over,
if I set the marble.
This grave will always remain like this.
Mainly because
It’s a life that’s been stolen.
Mario devotes his life to memory
of his son so that justice can be done.
Gianluca died for defending
his father-in-law who was a racketeer.
- In all cars and family,
there are photos of Gianluca.
Unlike many
families from Siderno,
Mario decided not to put
the veil on the murder of Gianluca.
So that the murderer is condemned,
Mario became a civil party,
something rare in the region.
Today the murderer risks
to leave for procedural violation.
For Mario to withdraw from the appeal trial,
the Ndrangheta, is putting pressure again.
- As I was threatened, thanks to these cameras,
I can control what
happens in front of my house,
and who enters my house.
The clan that killed his son
increases intimidation,
since the start of the procedure
judicial, almost 10 years ago.
- Do you see there?
- What is this ?
- These are projectile holes.
- And who shot?
- We don't know who shot.
How do you want us to know?
The last threat was
from a few months ago.
- We found a can of gasoline
right outside the door.
An act of intimidation to say to shut up.
“Keep quiet.”
- Was it during the trial?
- Yes, during the trial.
It was a clear signal.
Despite the risks, Mario puts everything
working so that the murderer of his son,
be definitively condemned.
- You never had the idea of ​​you
stop obeying this intimidation?
- Stop me? Absolutely not.
It didn't even cross my mind.
- The fight to the end?
- I will fight to the death.
Hoping it's natural.
Between extortion and drug trafficking,
the Ndrangheta reaps every year,
billions in cash.
To whiten them,
she carries out financial arrangements
sophisticated people in tax havens.
She only invests a small amount
part in Calabria, in stone.
In Brancaleone, Salvatore Aquino is suspected
to have joined forces with another sponsor,
to launder 200 million euros
by investing dirty money,
in this real estate program intended
to British people in need of sun.
6 years ago, Marie decided to leave
England for southern Italy.
- This is the swimming pool at the Émeraude residence.
Gioiello del mare, in French,
"The jewel of the sea",
charming residence of 400 apartments and
several villas facing the sea, 4 swimming pools,
this is what the DVD
promotion highlights,
to make customers like her dream.
Without forgetting the shopping center
at the foot of the building, land
tennis and a magnificent golf course.
However, today, the account is not there.
In 2012, the police put
end of all work.
It is then that Marie discovers
that this real estate program,
is in fact an important operation
bleaching of the Ndrangheta.
- The financial policy is
came to seal the doors,
of all the apartments which did not have
not yet been fully paid.
Since then, Marie has lived here alone all year round.
For her, it is in some way
double punishment.
She no longer has an apartment in London,
and she can't sell that of
Brancaleone while the investigation is ongoing.
- It's difficult because we don't know
not yet what will happen.
- And all your savings went there?
- These are the savings of a lifetime
who passed through this apartment.
And all that for living in a construction site.
It's already been 4 years since
the instruction has begun.
The affair involves 5 officials
corrupt municipal authorities,
and a suspected straw man
for having set up this real estate project,
very suspicious for the account
of godfathers of the Ndrangheta.
We found this man
5 kilometers from the residence.
He runs a small car dealership
far from prestigious real estate.
It's about this man
with the blue sweater.
Under house arrest, he is known
of Italian justice.
He has already served time in prison for
international trafficking of h****.
He is considered a member
influential in the Ndrangheta.
We film it on a hidden camera.
He claims everything is legal
in this real estate transaction,
that the money is not coming
from the mafia but from the banks.
- They made a big mistake,
huge mistake indeed.
They put it all together, it's all fake.
The man even cries of a conspiracy which would aim
to put him back behind bars.
- Why didn't you
managed to complete the project?
- Because they arrested me.
The magistrates arrested me.
It's all a conspiracy of the
politics and the judiciary.
This car dealership would not
so what an honest businessman?
And yet, he risks 15 years in prison for
his alleged involvement in this money laundering.
While waiting for the trial to end,
the apartments of the residence,
will remain sealed.
Italian justice confiscates each
year in Calabria dozens of buildings,
built by mafiosi, whether
to the clans that rule the villages
of L'aspromonte, or to families who have
control over entire neighborhoods,
from Reggio Calabria, the capital of the region.
Claude Chevalanidi is a
poor suburb of the city,
an abandoned place where homes
rub shoulders with unfinished buildings,
but already inhabited.
Here, the mafiosi don't hide
not their fortunes.
The godfather even had this built
cozy house on top of the hill.
Fallen for murder, he
never lived in this residence.
It was confiscated and entrusted
at the Ndrangheta observatory,
an association fighting against the mafia,
which takes care in particular of handing over
young delinquents on the straight and narrow.
It's Vincenzo, the director,
who now uses this house.
- This is the view from the terrace.
- This allowed the boss to
monitor its entire territory.
- Certainly yes.
It had a panoramic view
very complete of the area.
The best materials were
used such as marble,
from floor to ceiling in this bathroom.
- This is the bathroom
that he was being built,
with a view of the sea.
For 2 months, Vincenzo and his
colleagues from the Observatory,
receive here minors who
had to deal with the law.
These young people dealt
drugs or stole a car.
Most of them border the Ndrangheta
every day.
Juvenile justice requires them to follow
a reintegration program at the Observatory.
Its goal is to break
the image of the mafia,
and its promises of easy money.
- Here is one of the places
the most importants,
the place where most
fleeing criminals are hiding.
To create a spark among young people,
Vincenzo makes them in particular
visit a secret room.
- It's more than important, it's symbolic,
because it represents a way of life,
which is often mythologized.
We try, before demystifying it,
to make people understand that being a boss,
a mafioso, is not
an enviable thing at all.
At the foot of this ladder, a small
room of 10 square meters,
with rudimentary comfort.
The godfather had also planned a bunker.
Incarcerated, he was never able to complete it.
Vincenzo made the replica there
from a famous hiding place in Calabria.
- It is a fairly faithful reconstruction
from a bunker from 10 or 15 years ago.
Used by Bellocchio,
a mafioso from Rosarno.
When we found him,
we saw this sentence on the wall:
“God, protect me in this bunker.”
And he had hung all these
holy images that protected him.
He also had these wolves, because in
the mafia, they nicknamed him The Wolf.
What do you guys say?
- It was certainly,
a difficult lifestyle.
Really ugly.
For me, it's like detention.
It's living underground.
It's a rat's life.
Vincenzo addresses the delicate subject
of belonging to the Ndrangheta.
- When you enter,
you completely lose your freedom.
You no longer belong to you.
You belong to another person.
Your freedom, your lifestyle is
completely dependent on a third party.
- Your person no longer exists,
she is submissive to the boss.
- But according to you, what is fascinating?
- It's having money, a reputation,
have everything you want.
Because for a boy our age,
have money or a nice car
in this period, and very
few people can afford it.
And it’s also to stand out,
to appear as the greatest.
That’s what’s fascinating.
Vincenzo does prevention by
exploiting the assets seized from the mafiosi.
Another man grabbed it for them
grow and create jobs.
His name is Pino Demazzi.
In Italy, everyone knows him,
because he was the first priest,
to refuse to celebrate
the funeral of a godfather.
A punishment more humiliating than
prison for these criminals who are so religious.
Today, Pino Demazzi continues the affront.
He created a cooperative which manages and
exploits assets seized from the mafia.
- Confiscated land that
now manages the cooperative,
all belonged to families
very important of the Ndrangheta.
Only well-known names which today
still hold in their hands,
a large part of the national economy.
Don Pino makes work
dozens of people,
in a region where
unemployment reaches 40%.
The priest wants to show that he is
possible to work legally,
despite the pressure exerted by
the Ndrangheta on employees.
- People sometimes say: "But you are
mad! What did you go do?”
But in the end, this is the result
who counts, we create work.
Fear is just a feeling
and a feeling can be controlled.
Warnings are not
not empty words.
The mafia has already taken action,
she no longer lets go of Pino Demazzi,
since he recovered
neighboring olive groves.
Pino finds Domenico,
the president of the cooperative
- We have just finished picking.
He wants to show us
the traces of reprisals.
- Look, here, we see
still the old strain.
We put dirt on it.
Here, just before confiscation
definitive, before the assignment,
they came here with trucks,
chainsaws and cut down these trees.
Trees centuries old.
Some were very high, 10 to 15 meters.
6 years ago, the Ndrangheta
cut in one night,
these 640 ancestral olive trees for
leave nothing to Pino Demazzi.
The mafia would have resold
wood for more than €600,000.
3 years ago, the mafia again
tried to make him understand,
that these lands belonged to him.
This olive grove suffered a sad fate.
Hundreds of trees were burned.
The godfathers of the local clan who
had organized these destructions,
were sentenced to 16 years
from prison last year.
But these heavy sentences did not
not calmed the anger of Pino Demazzi.
- Finding yourself face to face with
land in this state,
see things like that,
it makes you angry.
Cutting down trees does not mean
not only the money goes to us.
That means :
"These trees are ours,
and no one else."
With thousands of young people
unemployed, often adrift,
the Ndrangheta is not near
to disappear from the Calabrian landscape.
Unless she finds on her way
a new major enemy, the Church.
Pope Francis visited
in Calabria last year.
- The Ndrangheta.
It is the worship of evil,
against the common good.
They are not in communion with
God, they are excommunicated.
Excommunication is an infamy,
the worst punishment for these criminals,
who venerate the Blessed Virgin
and the Archangel Saint Michael.